"Pine Mouth Syndrome: Prolonged
Bitter Taste from Certain Pine Nuts "
The reason I make my pesto with walnuts
instead of the more traditional pine nuts
is not only because walnuts
are probably healthier —
we're talking 20 times
more polyphenols —
but also because of a mysterious
phenomenon known as PMS.
Nope, not that PMS.
Pine Mouth Syndrome, characterized
by what has become my favorite
word of the week: cacogeusia,
meaning a bad taste in your mouth.
You can get it from heavy metal toxicity,
seafood toxins, certain nutritional
and neurologic disorders, or from
eating the wrong kind of pine nuts.
Termed "Pine Mouth" by the public,
a few days after eating pine nuts
you get this persistent metallic
or bitter taste in your mouth
that can last for weeks. Thousands
of cases have been reported.
Raw versus cooked pine nuts
doesn't seem to matter.
Could the cause be some
unidentified toxin present in some
varieties of non-edible pine nuts?
Out of more than 100 different kinds
of pine trees, the nuts of only about
30 are considered to be edible.
So pine nut samples from stricken
consumers were analyzed,
and indeed they all contained
nuts from Chinese white pine,
which is not reported to be edible. That
tree is typically only used for lumber.
These are the good ones;
these are the bad ones.
It's like a game: good,
bad, good, good.
You don't know it's the Chinese
white pine nuts, though,
until you put it to the test.
Researchers had a few folks consume
six to eight Chinese white pine nuts.
Most of the subjects hadn't ever
heard of Pine Mouth syndrome,
and, boom, they all developed
symptoms. We still don't know
exactly what it is in those nuts
that causes such a weird reaction.
We just know to stay away
from those kinds of pine nuts.
So what kinds of pine nuts do
we have on our shelves here?
All kinds apparently, including
those associated with pine mouth.
Good, good, good, bad, good.
So, unsurprisingly, hundreds of cases
have been reported in the U.S. as well.
Most of the implicated nuts
were reportedly labeled
as originating from Asia,
and in most cases China.
Europe actually did something
about it and demanded China stop
sending them toxic nuts,
which they did in 2011.
And this export restriction likely
resulted in less being imported
into the U.S. as well, given the
decline in cases going into 2012.
Rare cases still happen,
though, as evidenced by
an active Facebook group
entitled "Damn You Pine Nuts."
The primary reason I made
this video is just to allay fears
should this ever happen to you.
Although there are no proven therapies,
Pine Mouth syndrome appears to be
benign and just goes away on its own.